Irvin I. Rubin Papers
Irvin I. Rubin Papers
1940-2007
Rubin, Irvin I.
10 linear ft.
Professional papers related to the career of Plastics Hall of Fame member Irvin I. Rubin; including correspondence, company records, illustrations and other materials related to injection molding companies Robinson Plastics Corp. and Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corp.; texts and illustrations used in Rubin's writing about injection molding; and copies of many of his publications.
3304696
Biographical History
Irvin I. Rubin (1919- ) is an American chemist, engineer, businessman, author and educator who developed many technical processes in the plastics industry, especially in the field of injection molding.
Rubin received his BS in chemistry in 1938 at City College of New York and earned credits at Brooklyn College towards his Masters. His career in plastics began in 1940 as technical director of the molding plant of Robinson Plastics Corp., in New York City (the company later relocated to Hoboken, New Jersey). From 1942 to 1945, he was chief shift chemist at Montrose Chemical Co., in charge of producing tri-cresyl phosphate plasticizer for PVC cable for the war effort. From 1945 to 1946, he ran the manufacturing plant of Columbia Plastic Products, which fabricated acrylic products.
In 1946, Rubin joined Robinson Plastic Corporation. In 1967, he purchased the company and became its president. He was responsible for injection molding, designing, engineering, and production. From 1962, he was president and owner of Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corp., a manufacturer of plastics medical devices and equipment.
Rubin’s technical contributions to the industry include the development of vacuum metalizing on polystyrene as a commercial process for industrial lamp parts. Also significant was the development of internal carving and coloring of fabricated acrylic parts. In the late 1960s he assisted in the production of the first injection molded thoracic drainage system -- a process that is now standard.
In the 1960s, Rubin published his first series of technical articles. His first book, Theory and Practice of Injection Molds and Molding, was published in 1972. In 1977, he wrote the chapter on injection molds and molding in Introduction to Polymer Science and Technology.
In 1990, he edited the Handbook of Plastics Materials and Technology and wrote the chapter on injection molds and molding in the Society of the Plastics Industry (SPI) Plastics Engineering Handbook.
He is a Fellow of the Society of Plastics Engineers (SPE). He has served as president of the New York Section, vice chairman of 1955 ANTEC, chairman of the Publications Committee, chairman of I.T. Quarnstrom Foundation, president of the Plastics Molders Guild, consultant to the New York City Board of Education, and as an expert witness in state and federal courts. Rubin was inducted into the Plastics Hall of Fame in 1994.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Irvin I. Rubin Papers span the period 1940-2007 and focus primarily on business records of the Robinson Plastics Corp. and on Rubin’s research files for various lectures and writing projects. The records consist of personal records; correspondence; financial records and product literature related to Robinson Plastics Corp. and the Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corp; photographs and slides, product literature, hand drawings, technical drawings and research files related to injection molding; articles, chapter and book drafts, proofs, illustrations and offprints of Rubin's publications; and videotapes of plastics educational seminars produced by Learning Visions, Inc. Many file series retain the folder names applied by Rubin.
Biographical material contains records that relate to professional memberships and certificates and awards; material related to the Brooklyn Jewish Center Dinner-Dance (1974, 1979, 1983), and a photo of Rubin at the Vic Braden Tennis College (1987).
Companies contains a wide variety of production, management and marketing materials related to Rubin's career spent working for, managing and as owner of the Robinson Plastics Corporation and the Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corp. Titles to most of these files are those given by Rubin.
Consulting and expert witness work (1988-1996) contains invoices and bills related to Rubin's consulting work as an expert witness, and some statements regarding legal action including Lemelson Patents vs Mattel (1990), Capitol Vial, Inc. and Capitol Spouts, Inc. (1994), and Armament Systems and Procedures vs. Team Tooling, Inc. (1996).
Correspondence includes a variety of Rubin's correspondence, especially with publishers.
Illustrations contain many versions of original and collected charts, tables, diagrams, photographs mostly related to Rubin's many articles, chapters and books related to injection molding. Many of these same illustrations are found in his writings and as slides. Titles to most of these files are those given by Rubin.
Lectures contains texts, slide lists and publicity related to Rubin's conference papers, professional seminars and invited lectures, arranged chronologically.
Photographs and slides includes photographs, photographic negative and slides pertaining to Rubin's companies and especially a large number of 35 mm slides prepared as illustrations for his lectures about injection molding and other processes. Many slides are numbered; numbers correspond to accompanying lists.
Product literature contains an assortment of company brochures and catalogues related to specific products or lines of products including plastics and plastics molding machinery. Titles of most of these brochures are provided.
Products by Rubin contains production, marketing and sales documents related to particular products molded by Robinson Plastics Corp. or Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corp.
Research files primarily contain folders of periodical articles and ephemera related to different aspects of injecting molding researched and written by Rubin in many books and articles. Folders are divided and titled following Rubin’s organization. Individual articles are not catalogued.
Rolodex contains Rolodex address cards, especially those of clients and manufacturers.
Society of Plastics Engineers (SPE) (1951-1959) consists of programs and correspondence relating to the SPE's annual technical conferences (ANTEC) from 1951-1975. Rubin was Vice Chairman of Arrangements for the 15th ANTEC (1958-1959) and moderator at the 20th ANTEC (1963).
Videotapes contains a selection of videotapes and cassettes of seminars presented by Visual Learning, Inc., a company co-founded by Rubin. The collection includes two tapes of a Rubin seminar on injection molding.
Writings contain manuscripts, typescripts and offprints of articles, chapters and books written by Rubin, arranged chronologically.
Artifact records contains photographs and data sheets for more than 100 plastic items donated by Rubin to the Plastics Center and Museum. The items themselves are now part of the
Plastics Artifacts Collection
, and may be seen at The Plastics Collection website.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic. With the exception of Lectures and Writings, which are arranged chronologically, folders for all topics are also arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
A large selection of plastic objects molded by Irvin I. Rubin and his companies are part of the
Plastics Artifacts Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Rubin, Irvin I., 1919-; Atlas, Sheldon M.; Beall, Glenn.; Frizelle, William G.; Kaufman, Herman S.; Robinson, Sol M.; Shook, Gerald D.; Robinson Plastics Corporation.; Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corporation.; Society of Plastics Engineers.; Plastics Hall of Fame.; Brooklyn Jewish Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Vic Braden Tennis College.; John Chatillon & Sons.; Gametime, Inc.; Sonics International.; Daysol International.; Circular Crib Co., Inc.; Program for the Introduction and Adaptation of Contraceptive Technology (U.S.); Capitol Vial, Inc.; Capitol Spouts, Inc.; Armament Systems and Procedures.; Team Tooling, Inc.; Gulton Industries.; Plastics industry and trade -- Technological innovations.; Plastics industry and trade -- United States -- History.; Injection molding of plastics.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Correspondence.; Interviews.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Technical reports.; Videocassettes.; Video recordings.; Engineers.; Inventors.; Businessmen.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Irvin I. Rubin, 2010.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Articles about Irvin I. Rubin (Box 1)
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Jewish Center, 1974-1983; materials related to Rubin's organization of dinner dance (Box 1)
  - Chemical History Foundation, 2002; oral history notes (Box 1)
  - Quarnstrom Foundation board, 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Vic Braden Tennis College, 1987 (Box 1)
- Companies
  - Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corp.
    - A-4005 processing procedures, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
    - Daysol invoices and receipts, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Financial, 1979-1988 (Box 1)
    - Molds, 1986-1993 (Box 1)
  - Robinson Lamp Parts
    - Financial and sale, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Robinson Plastics Corp.
    - About molding (Box 1)
    - Financial, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Floor plan, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Invoices (Box 1)
    - Job receipts, 1973-1985 (Box 1)
    - Machines (Box 1)
    - Mold drawings, 1967-78 (Box 1)
    - Mold repair (Box 1)
    - Molds, 1972-1986 (Box 1)
    - Mold lists, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
    - Mold lists correspondence, 1983-1993 (Box 2)
    - Pension plan (Box 2)
    - Public relations (Box 2)
    - Sales agent agreement, 1954-1962 (Box 2)
    - Stock sales, 1961-1970 (Box 2)
    - Union (Box 2)
    - Valuation, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
- Consulting and expert witness
  - Armaments Systems, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Capitol Vial vs. Capitol Spouts, 1994 (Box 3)
  - DuPont, 1993 (Box 3)
  - International Medical Technology, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Lemelson Patents vs. Mattel, 1990 (Box 3)
  - PATH (Program for Appropriate Technology in Health), 1981-1990 (Box 3)
  - 3M Lens, 1988 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  - Book research, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Hanker Publisher, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Injection Molding Magazine re: nomination of Glenn Beall for award, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Rubin - Van Nostrand, 1986-1987; correspondence requesting Rubin's comments on John Delmonte proposal for metal-filled plastics book (Box 3)
  - Styrofoam cups and recycling, 1988-1990; correspondence and materials related to Rubin's public pronouncements in print and on television in response to calls for banning Styrofoam containers (Box 3)
  - Wiley & Sons correspondence, 1978-1993; correspondence with publisher of the Handbook of Plastics Materials and Technology (Box 3)
  - Wiley & Sons royalty statements, 1990s; royalty statements for the Handbook of Plastics Materials and Technology (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1967 (Box 3)
- Illustrations
  - Final (Box 4)
  - Handbook of plastics materials and technology camera-ready artwork, 1990; 2 folders (Oversize 1)
  - Handbook of plastics materials and technology camera-ready artwork, 1990; 3 folders (Oversize 2)
  - Hydraulic and electric, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - IMPCO for slides (Box 4)
  - Injection molding for Wiley Handbook, 1980s (Box 4)
  - JRR (Box 4)
  - Machinery (Box 4)
  - Machine circuits (Box 4)
  - Machines, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Mold drawings (Box 4)
  - Mold parts (Box 5)
  - Molds, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Molding machines (Box 5)
  - Pressure (Box 5)
  - Pumps (Box 5)
  - Other processes (Box 5)
  - SME masters (Box 5)
  - Theory, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Valves (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Lectures
  - Consultants to the plastics industry, 1969; brochures for workshop seminars (Box 6)
  - Slide lists, 1970-1999 (Box 6)
  - Plastics in Appliances Conference, 1973; programs for continuing education conference at New York University (Box 6)
  - Visual Learning, Inc, 1973; brochures for Focus on Learning seminars; audio visual training tapes from Visual Learning, Inc., a company co-founded by Louis I. Naterman and Irvin Rubin (Box 6)
    See also Videotapes: Visual Learning, Inc. for videotapes of these seminars
  - National symposium, Newark, NJ, 1977; programs for national symposium: the design and construction of tooling for plastics, and text of Rubin's presentation: A review of hot runner systems, hot sprue bushing and gating. (Box 6)
  - Injection mold design, 1978; brochures for seminar by Irvin Rubin offered by Plastic design forum magazine and Plastics Machinery & Equipment Magazine (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-2000 (Box 6)
- Photographs and slides
  - Apollo 12 from NASA (Box 6)
  - Auto, 35 mm slides labeled Auto; approximately 80 slides (Box 6)
  - Black and white negatives (molding), 7 negative envelopes; envelopes are labeled: hydraulic components, circuits, pumps; misc; machines, other processes; electrical components, electrical circuits; molds; rheology, molding; molded parts (Box 6)
  - Black and white negatives (of slides) (Box 6)
  - Hot runner systems, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Humor, 35 mm slides of cartoons, mostly from Playboy Magazine; approximately 80 slides (Box 6)
  - Hunkar, 35 mm slides labeled Hunkar; approximately 20 slides (Box 6)
  - Incoe corporation, 35 mm slides from Incoe Corporation, Troy, Michigan; approximately 40 slides (Box 7)
  - Kona Corporation, 35 mm slides from Kona Corporation, Gloucester, Massachusetts; approximately 20 slides (Box 7)
  - McAuto, 35 mm slides labeled McAuto (or McAoto?); approximately 40 slides (Box 7)
  - Mold cooling, 35 mm slides marked "Gamma, Chicago"; approximately 40 slides (Box 7)
  - Monsanto, 35 mm slides from Monsanto; approximately 60 slides (Box 7)
  - People, 35 mm slides of people, mostly from Robinson plastic corp., including Irvin Rubin; approximately 20 slides (Box 7)
  - Robinson Plastics Corp., 1961; black and white negative and prints including Michelin man, company staff and facilities (Box 7)
  - Robinson Plastics Corp. promotional photos, large format negatives and prints of Robinson products and production machines (Box 7)
  - Rubin products, 35 mm slides of products molded by Irvin Rubin, including some objects donated to SCRC plastics collection; approximately 60 slides (Box 7)
  - Tenite process flow (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 35 mm slides, mostly of molding machines and processes; approximately 320 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled D, 35 mm slides; approximately 220 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled DC, 35 mm slides; approximately 80 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled DME, 35 mm slides; approximately 60 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled GR, 35 mm slides; approximately 40 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled HC, 35 mm slides; approximately 20 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled MM for mold master, 35 mm slides; approximately 20 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled OP, 35 mm slides; approximately 100 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled PR, 35 mm slides; approximately 60 slides (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous labeled SP, 35 mm slides; approximately 20 slides (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous labeled TM, 35 mm slides; approximately 20 slides (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous labeled V, 35 mm slides; approximately 40 slides (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous numbered 1-500, 3 folders; 35 mm slides; approximately 260 slides (Box 8)
- Product literature
  - American Chain & Cable Company, 1957; Wilson Mechanical Instrument Division, catalog RT58, 44-page booklet on Rockwell hardness tester (Box 9)
  - Atlas Press Company, 8-page parts price list for 10 inch F series Atlas lathes (Box 9)
  - Avnet Shaw Corporation, 1962; 62-page booklet: The Shaw Process (Box 9)
  - Baldwin Locomotive Works, 1946; 40-page booklet: Hydraulic Tables and Other Data (Box 9)
  - Buffalo Forge Company, 12-page booklet: Maintenance Manual and Spare Parts Catalog, Buffalo No. 15 Drills (Box 9)
  - Celanese Plastics Company, 1969; 20-page Bulletin P1A: Fortiflex Polyethylene Properties; 28-page booklet, Bulletin G1C, 9th edition: Standard Tests on Plastics (Box 9)
  - Dow Chemical Company, 1965; 18-page booklet: Chemical Resistance Permanence (Box 9)
  - Elgin National Watch Company, 1955; 8-page booklet: Metallographic Polishing with Diamond (Box 9)
  - Ferro Corporation, 1962; 40-page booklet: Coloring Plastics, by James E. Simpson (Box 9)
  - General Electric, 2-sided Noryl thermoplastic resins processing guide: Designing for press fits (Box 9)
  - Greenfield Tap and Die Corporation, 1945; 52-page booklet: Guide to Screw Thread Fits (Box 9)
  - Hughes Aircraft Company, 10-page booklet from Electron Dynamics Division: Heat Pipe Technology for Industry (Box 9)
  - Husky, 1967; 1975,; 1981-1982; newsletters (Box 9)
  - Instron Engineering Corp., 1958; 1962; Application series PC-3 and PC-12 (offprints): A high shear capillary rheometer for polymer melts by E.H. Merz and R.E. Colwell; Rheology of molten polymers by Giovanni Pezzin (Box 9)
  - Koppers Company, 8-page booklet: Dylan & Super Dylan Polyethylenes (Box 9)
  - Monsanto (Box 9)
  - Phillips Chemical Company, 1959; 20-page booklet: Technical Information on Marlex Polyethylene (Box 9)
  - Roll, Die and Mold Decorators, Inc., 24-page booklet: Texturing Suggestions (Box 9)
  - Shell Chemical Company, 1968; 12-page booklet: Injection molding of KRATON rubber (Box 9)
  - Stilson, circa 1976; 9-page booklet: Wedge Lock Actuators (Box 9)
  - Udeholm Limited, Two catalogues for stainless steel tools including 13-page booklet: Steels for molds (Box 9)
  - Westinghouse Air Brake Company, 1957-1958; 28-page booklet: Basic Pneumatic Control; 24-page booklet: Devices and Fundamentals of Air Circuitry (Box 9)
- Products by Rubin
  - Buttons (Box 9)
  - Candle holders, 1966-1969 (Box 9)
  - Cigarette lighter, promotional material from Gulton Industries for cigarette lighter with rechargeable nickel cadmium battery (Box 9)
  - Clinique mascara applicator, 1977; 7 items (Map-case 97)
    Two large measured pencil on vellum drawings for molds for Clinique small container sleeve and drawer, labeled AID JOB #7177, each 44 inches x 36 inches
    Five measured pencil on vellum drawings labeled sheets 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 for otherwise unidentified AID JOB #7199
    These came rolled with Clinique drawings and probably relate to some aspect of the job.
  - Circular crib (Box 9)
  - Decorative extension rods, promotional materials from the Gould-Mersereau Co., Inc. for decorative extension rods (Box 9)
  - Fruit slicer, 1947 (Box 9)
  - Games (Box 9)
  - Handbags, promotional material from Rialto products for plastic handbags (Box 9)
  - Lamp parts (Box 9)
  - Lapidary tumbler, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Party & patio (Box 9)
  - Plastic projectiles, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Pleur-Evac, 1979-1984 (Box 9)
  - Sarama 4-piece garden light, 1975; blueprints for molds; 11 items (Box 10)
  - Sarama window panel, 1976; blueprint for molds by Emidio Maria Da Silva, Mirinha Grande, Portugal (Box 10)
  - Shop-Vac (Box 10)
  - Skimmer and pump (Box 10)
  - Snap Jack, 1976; blueprints for molds by Tri-A-Tool & Mold Co., Inc, Linden, New Jersey; 12 items (Box 10)
  - Spring scale, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Tempo (Box 10)
  - Toothbrushes and holder (Box 10)
- Research files
  - AT&T Technology Systems, 1985 (Box 10)
  - CREEP, etc (Box 10)
  - Die hobbing, 1945; offprint of "The procedure of die hobbing" by Islyn Thomas and John Hohl, reprinted from Modern Plastics Magazine (January 1945) (Box 10)
  - Electrical (Box 10)
  - Forming cavities (Box 10)
  - Gates (Box 10)
  - Heat pins (Box 10)
  - Hot runners (Box 10)
  - Hydraulic references (Box 11)
  - Identifying plastics (Box 11)
  - Ives, Frank, Sep 2001; issue of Composites Fabrication with article about Ives (Box 11)
  - Machines (Box 11)
  - Mold base (Box 11)
  - Mold design (Box 11)
  - Mold machine (Box 11)
  - Molding, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Molds (Box 11)
  - Nozzles and return valves (Box 11)
  - Orientation / flow (Box 11)
  - Polymer Engineering and Science, 1969-1979; tables of contents and invoice (Box 11)
  - Press safety (Box 12)
  - Temperature (Box 12)
  - Temperature control (Box 12)
  - Theory, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Twin screws (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 13)
- Rolodex
  - Address cards, Rubin plastics clients, distributors and mold manufacturers; 4 folders (Box 13)
- Society of Plastics Engineers (SPE)
  - Annual Technical Conference (ANTEC), 1951-1975; copies of letters from Rubin regarding organization of 1959 SPE 15th ANTEC and programs from others' ANTECs (Box 14)
  - Expenses, 1989-1997 (Box 14)
  - Lecture invoices and evaluations, 1997 (Box 14)
  - Seminars, 1973-1981; brochures and information about SPE educational seminars of 1973, 1974 and 1981 in which Rubin lectured on injection molding (Box 14)
  - Slides of programs and people, 1949-1957 (Box 14)
  - SPE Journal articles, 1950s-1960s (Box 14)
  - Technical conference papers, 1981 (Box 14)
  - Technical papers, 1964-1968; technical papers from the regional technical conferences: "Advances in Moldmaking and Mold Design," "New designs for mold construction," "Plastics in the medical sciences," and "The promise of thermosets." (Box 14)
  - Technical papers, 1972-1973; technical papers from the regional technical conferences: "Automation in processing" and "Predicting plastics performance" (Box 14)
  - Vinyl Technology Newsletter, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1955-1966 (Box 14)
- Videotapes, Visual Learning, Inc.
  See also Lectures: Visual Learning, Inc.
  - Injection molding, by Irvin I. Rubin, part 1, rubin_i_001; mold description, characterization, design approach, parting line; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; 1 U-matic videocassette (Box 15)
  - Injection molding, by Irvin I. Rubin, part 3, rubin_i_002; materials, hardening, mold construction, gate design; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; 1 U-matic videocassette (Box 15)
  - Introduction to polymer science, by Herman S. Kaufman, part of Visual Plastics Learning series; rubin_i_003; 1 U-matic videocassette (Box 15)
    Covers history of polymer science, what polymers are, definitions, how polymers are made, structure of polymers, solid state properties, polymer property and structure relationships, rheological properties, mechanical properties, properties and relationship to processing.
  - Introduction to polymer science by Herman S. Kaufman, part of Visual Plastics Learning series; rubin_i_004; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 15)
  - Plastic materials description and selection, by Sheldon M. Atlas, Part 1, rubin_i_006; thermoplastics; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; reel-to-reel tape (Box 15)
  - Plastic materials description and selection, by Sheldon M. Atlas, Part 2, rubin_i_005; thermoplastics; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; 1 U-matic videocassette (Box 15)
  - Real properties of plastic testing and evaluation, by William G. Frizelle, part 2, rubin_i_008; fluid properties under flow conditions; 1 U-matic videocassette (Box 15)
  - Real properties of plastic testing and evaluation, by William G. Frizelle, part 2, fluid properties under flow conditions; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; rubin_i_010; reel-to-reel tape (Box 15)
  - Real properties of plastic testing and evaluation, by William G. Frizelle, may be part 2 (fluid properties under flow conditions); label very faded; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; rubin_i_009; reel-to-reel tape (Box 15)
  - Reinforced plastics lecture, by Gerald D. Shook, part 1, rubin_i_011; history, materials, design, bonding and foams; part of Visual Plastics Learning series; 2 U-matic videocassettes (Box 15)